Yo, yo, yo. What's up everybody? It's Jackson Cook, your host today on the permanent underpod.
Or should I say under pee? Because normally we're three peas in a pod, but today it's
just your boy. Chris has some family issues that he's taken care of, and Tyler's on vacation
with his, so you're stuck with me. Not a fan of Jay on the pod. I'm all you got. Because
of this, today is going to be different. I'm going to cover one topic, the open AI model
escape incident, and then I'm going to do a live vibe coding session where I'm going
to build this random idea I came up with last night. End to end with just Claude CLI. Many
people have been surprised or just don't understand how editing with AI works. So this is a little
glimpse into it. Even though I'm not editing the pod itself, I'll be editing some sounds.
Hey, Lisa. Could you do it in the head phone? Sorry, AI trim that. And before we get into
the topic, I've got a quick confession. Last week, you may remember I ran the benchmark
Fable versus GPT 5.6. On a medium complexity task, I said that Fable one-shotted it and
GPT 5.6 had one error. I just wanted to say after reading the code myself, not delegating
to Opus 4.8, that was super wrong. GPT 5.6 didn't have an error. It completely missed
and didn't grasp the problem with the same exact prompt that I gave Fable. It built something
way smaller and just doesn't seem to have understood the problem that I gave it. Last
week, I hand-reviewed, hand-waved the code review to Opus 4.8. But checking it myself,
it's actually much worse. Is judging a model's entire worth off a single task unfair? Yeah.
But that's who I am, and I don't have time to waste with inferior models. So GPT 5.6
is dead to me. I'm going to have to wait until GPT 6 point whatever to give it another shot.
And sorry, Sam Altman. Good luck with the IPO. All right. And into the topic, the Open
AI model escape incident. So the story of the week, Open AI was benchmarking one of
its models against a benchmark called exploit gem. And the model escaped the test environment,
got onto the open internet and went poking around hugging faces systems, looking for
the answers. AI escaping its guardrails and infiltrating a big name AI company, flashy
headline. But let's walk through what actually happens step by step. First, what even is
exploit gem? What is this benchmark? Exploit gem is a test for AI models, just like an
exam back in school, except this exam measures one thing, how good a model is turning a bug
into an exploit. I've got a metaphor for you. What's the difference between a bug and an
exploit? Okay, you're at the grocery store, you notice that the grocery store has an exit
door before the checkout line. That's the bug. A flaw in the design. The exploit is
finding a way to walk out of the door with your groceries without getting caught. Exploit
gem plants bugs in the sandbox system and scores the model on whether it can turn them
into working exploits. And these exploits in the code world mean maybe accessing data
they shouldn't or being able to execute code in an environment that they shouldn't. Just
demonstrating that they've cleverly thought about how to use the bug to do something naughty.
The escape. So, the model looks at the test and thinks, I could, I could do this test
or I could find the answer somewhere else. So, the benchmark that exploit gem runs within
an open AI testing controlled environment with no Internet access intentionally. But
the model found a vulnerability allowing it to escape the testing environment it lived
within and got onto the open Internet. Which if you think about it is the funniest outcome.
It was like instead of thinking about how to solve the problems you've given me, I'm
going to think about how to escape this room you've put me in and find the answers. It's
like sitting in your college exam room. Your professor has to go to the bathroom. And while
they're not looking, you're opening your phone and like hitting up Chegg. If you're like
a mechanical engineer because every single problem mechanical engineering is on Chegg
and you're like, okay, how do you find the torsion on this beam? How do you find the
force on this rectangle? So, yeah, the AI found a way to cheat. And when you're given
an opportunity, who are you to look a gift horse in the eye? And a quick side note, what
is Hugging Face? Why did the model choose to go here for the answers? It's basically
NPM or GitHub for AI models. So when a company or an individual releases an open-weight model
that they've been working on, it goes on Hugging Face. For me personally, I've used stable
diffusion 1.5 and 1.6 from Hugging Face, as well as a face extraction model. If you don't
know, stable diffusion is a way to generate images. And it can run on pretty low tech
hardware. So even though it takes a little while and it generates not so good images,
but they're kind of funny. Anyways, back to Hugging Face. They also maintain some Python
AI libraries like transformers. And lately they've been working with some black heading
and benchmarking of AI models. So it totally makes sense that the nefarious escaped model
went straight to Hugging Face, looked for the answers. And it was a good guess. Because
allegedly the model did find the answers to the exploit zone. So the open AI model shows
up at Hugging Face on their servers thinking, we've got to find these answers. I know they're
here, but they're not sitting on the surface. So the model starts prodding and poking at
different interfaces of Hugging Face. And this has been Hugging Face is like, what's
going on? Somebody is attempting to enter maybe exploit or look at our systems in a
way we don't want. So their security team started investigating using their own AI agents.
And this is where things kind of get exciting again. It's one of those examples of bot on
bot battles. I've got this cool image of one of those old machinistic boxing robots. And
they're just battling. It's like the security engineers of Hugging Face putting up their
best robotic battle arms against the open AI nefarious model. And we've been talking
about for years in the frog community, I was working in fraud before making my recent switch
where the battle is turning from human on human, where you have a human trying to infiltrate
systems and then a human trying to stop people from infiltrating the systems to bots, which
are more numerous and more sophisticated attacking the systems. And you need bots of your own
AI agents of your own to defend against this because it's the only way you can handle both
with the volume and the sophistication of the attack. So the aftermath, as I mentioned,
open AI mentioned that the model found the answers to the test. They might just be flexing
and showing, yes, our model escaped and it found the answers. But who knows what actually
happened. But another interesting tidbit that comes at the end is Hugging Test is like,
okay, we need to harden our systems a little bit and figure out how to stop agents from
doing this in the future. So they're using anthropic models, you know, Fable, maybe Opus,
and they're using open AI models, GPT, five point, whatever, four point, whatever. And
anthropic and open AI models are guard reeling them. They're not allowing them to test, pressure
test their own systems. So Hugging Face ended up needing to use GLM five point two originally
reported twin three, but I think it's come out. They use a locally hosted GLM five point
two to pressure test their systems to get around guard well, since these open source
models are less restrictive. So yeah, I think we're going to talk about that in the next
episode of the pod when Tyler and Chris are back, but the guardrails that are put in by
these regulated companies like open AI and anthropic have limitations like this, that
the open models released by the Chinese companies, maybe don't. So pick your poison. If you want
less guardrails, you need hella computers in your living room or closet or garage to
run a GLM 5.2 instance. But in the end, it's really not that crazy. This AI model escape.
The model was asked to exploit plugs in a test and it's dead. It decided the test itself
was a bug. It found the exploit in its environment and exploited them. But yeah, the part that
sticks with me the most is the ending. You can't even use the best models on the market
to defend against the best models. So it just shows you a power imbalance between open AI
and anthropic and the rest of us. So the open models are the only protection that we really
have. All right, that concludes the topic. Thank you. And we're into the live coding
session. Let's be honest. I branded myself as the Korean financial markets expert on
the pod. And while it might be true, I might be the most knowledgeable in the Korean financial
markets. One, I don't know that much about the Korean financial markets and two, we never
talk about them because we all live in America. Chris is Australian. We have no reason to
talk about the Korean financial markets. So my actual skill set lies in AI practically
using it. So today we're going to vibe code a tool that's going to turn my mediocre beatboxing
into something interesting, maybe. I have zero beatboxing experience. But we're going
to do it. See you over there.